<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirituall spring A sermon preached at Pauls, vvherein is declared the necessity of growing in grace, and the goodly gaine that comes thereby, &amp;c. By Richard Lee, preacher of the word of God at Woluerhampton in Staffordshire.</title>
            <author>Lee, Richard, d. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1245:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirituall spring A sermon preached at Pauls, vvherein is declared the necessity of growing in grace, and the goodly gaine that comes thereby, &amp;c. By Richard Lee, preacher of the word of God at Woluerhampton in Staffordshire.</title>
                  <author>Lee, Richard, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Samuel Man, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:8843:1"/>
            <head>Errata ſic corrige.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. <hi>lin. penult. lege</hi> Incurrat. <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>lin.</hi> 4. defit. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 12. Legeruntne. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 3. quae. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 4. jure. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 8. nulla. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>vlt</hi> filij. <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 2. necquicquam.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8843:1"/>
            <p>The Spirituall Spring.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>PAVLS,</hi> Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> declared the neceſſity of growing in GRACE, and the goodly gaine that comes thereby, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD LEE, Preacher of the word of God at <hi>Woluerhampton</hi> in STAFFORDSHIRE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.16.</hi>
               </bibl> Awake, O North winde, and come thou South, blow vpon my Garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow out: Let my beloued come into his Garden, and eate his pleaſant fruits.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for SAMVEL MAN, dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Swan, 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8843:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8843:2"/>
            <head>To the VVorſhipfull, and his louing friende, the Gentlemen of <hi>London,</hi> Benefactors to the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word of God, at <hi>Woluerhampton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was firſt importun'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe my weake labours to a more generall view: I ſtood in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, whether way to take: On the one ſide, I ſaw the world was full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of Books: &amp; what good would my ſpoonfull doo in the Sea? and how vnfit it were that my ſelfe, the leaſt of littles, ſhould deliuer knowledge to poſterity, and that this wayward age, was ſo ill-diſpoſed, that it could not abide <hi>vngues in vlcere,</hi> we ſhould ſcratch in the ſore; as alſo the clowdie ſtile, and ſtumbling phraſe I had writ it in, not dreaming the world ſhould looke on it. Furthermore, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued on the other hand, that my ſcarce diſcerned ſparke, gaue a true light; and why may not ſome gaine a little?</p>
            <p>I haue read of night-trauellers, that haue beene refreſhed by the ſhine of Glow-wormes? Wee are borne in a time, wherein people loue new varieties in apparell, diet, houſes, yea, friends: why may not ſome ſee this, and be better for it? It is an ill winde blowes no man profit; If but one gaine, and that a little, I haue enough. A ſicke or weake ſtomacke, that at a table leaues dainties, and feedes of ſome courſe diſh, the Cooke will not repent he ſent it in.</p>
            <p>Being moued by theſe things, I thought I could not doe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to ſend it to your hands (although moſt of you heard it Preached) to expreſſe my thankfulnes for that loue and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality I haue receiued from many of you: and now I am glad, God hath giuen me this opportunity to lay open to wide report, that worthy worke you haue done amongſt vs. There is a curſed crying; Sin raignes in this age without controule,
<pb facs="tcp:8843:3"/>
I meane the taking away of Church-rites,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 18. in. Act.</note> called by <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, the dowrie of the Bride;</hi> robbing of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Church the Mother: Hence it is, that many braue wits turne to ſtudy Law, or Phyſicke, or follow ſome other callings, letting paſſe ſacred Diuinity, the Miſtreſſe of ſciences; and thoſe that haue taken on them that worthy fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet want of meanes, hath brought want of bookes and other neceſſaries; ſo that many ſtuffe their heads with eares in ſtead of learning; meane while the Goſpell droopes, Gods vine-tree ſpreads not, Popery holds his ground, &amp; duskie ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance as a thicke miſt remains vndiſpeld in many corners of this Kingdome, for want of ſun-beames. But the more we beate on this poynt, the harder mens hearts are; like the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadupes,</hi> that are deafe by the fall of <hi>Nilus.</hi> Now bleſſed be God, who hath ſo mightily wrought in you, to ſtirre you vp to bee inſtruments, to ſpreade heauens ſun-ſhine, to thoſe that ſit in darkeneſſe; and haue ſent labourers into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vineyards, and paid them with your owne penny. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie be the Angell that called on you, to ſend helpe into our <hi>Macedonia:</hi> I meane, to eſtabliſh the preaching of Gods word in that place where I now dwel. I neuer knew any part of this kingdome, where <hi>Romes</hi> ſhakie brood rooſted &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted themſelues more warmer and ſafer, and with greater countenance, then in our country. But I make no queſtion, it is begun already that as the day breakes, and the ſhadowes flye away, thoſe owles will betake themſeles to Iuie trees, and no longer dominere ouer the childiſh in experience of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Goe on worthy Gentlemen with ſuch workes, they ſhall be your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and crown. The Lord ſtir vp your hearts more and more, &amp; grant that others may glaſſe themſelues by you, and through your example, tread this holy maze. And ſo I reſt, committing my faint endeauours into your hands, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your fauorable acceptance, &amp; wonted loue. I ſhal remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours euer obliged,</hi> Richard Lee.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Woluerhampton</hi> 
                  <date>Octob. <hi>16. 1624.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8843:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Spirituall SPRING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 PETER 3. Verſe the laſt.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt: to him be glory both now and for euer, Amen:</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words in hand are a ſoueraigne remedy againſt the deadly poyſon of Apoſtacie. The Apoſtle tels vs a little before, that in theſe laſt and worſt times, many il-aduiſed men ſhall caſt vnſauoury ſcornes in the face of Chriſtian profeſſion, which ſhall cauſe many to faint in their iourney to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. A helpe againſt cold, is heate, againſt pouerty, is thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe; againſt going backward, is preſſing forward. We haue here pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enting-Phyſicke againſt relapſes, and rather doe water and manure Grace, then ſow it. We vrge not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but proſpering; rather foode to nouriſh, then ſeede to beget. Here is a ſingle act, with a double obiect, A charge giuen, expreſſing the matter, <hi>Grow,</hi> the ſubiect, in <hi>Grace and Knowledge;</hi> and ſo ſhuts vp the Epiſtle with a Doxologie at the foote of it.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Grow,</hi> is taken either <hi>continuè,</hi> to augment thoſe graces we haue: or <hi>Diſcretè,</hi> to adde new to our ſtore, as the ſame Apoſtle hath it, Chap. 5. <hi>adde to your faith vertue, &amp;c. Grace</hi> is taken either for Gods fauour in himſelfe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5.6. this is that which makes vs acceptable before him; Or for the gift of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. In God as in the Fountaine,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Jgnita enallag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ri</note> in vs as in the Ciſterne; he is the light, wee are as <hi>Iohn</hi> was, a burning lampe, enlightened from that light. <hi>Grace,</hi> one for more, Grace, for Graces. Or rather it is, <hi>vox artis,</hi> where grace ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies more than graces, <hi>cauſa</hi> then <hi>cauſa;</hi> as in the Scripture,<note place="margin">Si Chriſtum diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cis.</note> man is a larger word then <hi>men, Knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8843:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chdoche, to know and beleeue in him. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fountaine and head of all Religion, the end and perfection of the Law and Goſpell, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3. Grace is ſet before know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, becauſe a graceleſſe knowing is a fruitleſſe knowing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Growth</hi> here then muſt be an actiue motion, or opperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of graces of Gods ſpirit in vs, whereby they increaſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by appoſition or extenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct. —Haec noſtro ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur area curru.</note>You ſee now which way the words looke, and what ſmell the flowers bound-vp will ſend forth. The quinteſſentiall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or maine path, I muſt beate, is, that we muſt not onely be carefull to haue graces, but to increaſe in thoſe when they are begun. God would haue vs good Proficien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in his ſchoole, and to thriue vnder his hand, to mend our pace in our Chriſtian iourney, to build vpon the foundation alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy layd. Gods campe admits of no dwarfes, his flouriſhing paſtures of no ſtooklings, his family of no vnchriſts. It is that with Grace as with Nature, in growth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> makes to bee at a ſtand, and olde age makes to decay; but good men, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 84.7. <hi>they goe from ſtrength to ſtrength.</hi> The Prophet alludes to the growing of a childe, which as it multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies in yeares, waxeth ſtronger, <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 4.18. <hi>The iuſt ſhineth more and more vnto the perfect day.</hi> As in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reake of day, we haue a ſcarce-diſcerned light, after a while, the morning ſhewes her white limbe through nights black curtains, and ſo by degrees wins the field of darkneſſe, &amp; comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, yea to a golden ſplendor: In the like manner ſaith the Wiſe man, doth graces luſtre creepe on to perfection in Gods ſeruants. <hi>Dauid</hi> compares a Chriſtians goodneſſe to the ſpring-time, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 92.14 when all but rotten trees bud and bloſſome. In the Goſpell our Sauiour reprehends the ſloathfull ſeruant that puts not forth his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ent.<note place="margin">Math. 25. Math. 13.</note> Againe, he compares Grace vnto a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine of Muſtard ſeede, which is a very little ſeede, yet in ſome Countries is of ſo great a ſtalk, that birds may build their neaſts in it.<note place="margin">In Syria <hi>ſaith</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tan.</note> Thus you ſee God ſtands for it, how holy Writ bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth on it with ſprinkling brightneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note>Now Reaſon ſhall ſtand vp like an armed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to defend i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: Let vs briefly then conſider, his, the Neceſſity; ſecondly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8843:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, thirdly, the danger of not growing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Neceſſity pleads for it, becauſe; firſt, wee haue no ſet pitch in this life, we muſt reſt when wee are dead, here is our nonage, when we are at full age, to our inheritance we goe: This life is our ſpring-time, when we are ripe, God reapes vs into his barne: We are here as young Plants in a Nurſerie, when wee are growne vp, God will tranſplant vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Wee went on a pace in euill, in our vnregeneracie, when wee ſerued the diuell: haue not wee more reaſon to runne faſter now, hauing a better Maſter, a credibler ſeruice, and greater wages?</p>
            <p n="3">3 All will be little enough in times of tryall: Deſertions, temptations, ſickneſſes, croſſes, and death, will looke vs in the face. The wings of our hope will bee cut off, find our prayers will haue their moultring time; wee ſhall fight then againſt our ſelues like gyants: we gleane but happineſſe now, wee ſhall mow miſery then; ſtore will be no ſore, but a ſuperſedeas in all our tryals, let vs barrell vp plenty of grace, and feather our neaſts, &amp; prepare oyle in our lamps againſt that time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſee the benefits that accrew by our growing.</p>
            <p n="1">1 God ſhall haue much glory, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Herein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified, that ye bears much fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Themſelues ſhall haue much benefit by it;<note place="margin">Luke 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they that ſow much, ſhall reape much; to increaſe in grace, is to furniſh our ſelues with faith againſt tryals, with ioy in miſeries, ſtrength on thy death-bed, ability to pray, and the like: for he that doubled his fiue talents, was made Ruler ouer many things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21. <hi>His that ſoweth liberally,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall reape libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Others gaine by our wealth and gleane at our harueſt; We ſhall by our good inſtruction and examples ſet feathers to other folkes arrowes; when our hearbs are growne, we ſhall fraught our neighbours gardens; our light ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten them, our liues ſhall ſhame them, and ſet Conſcience on working; for the fuller the Fountaine is, the bigger the ſtreame will be.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the danger of not growing.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8843:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">Minimè verò bonus eſt, qui melior non vult fieri. Ber. ep. <hi>91.</hi> Qui melior eſſe non cupit nec eſt bonus.</note>1 Such haue no grace at all, onely guilded outſides. That ſeede which growes not, is rotten vnder the clods: He was neuer good that mends not: The goodneſſe of the ground is knowne by the crop.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Painted corne ripens not: theſe diſgrace the meanes God hath giuen them, as the Word and Sacraments; a leane-fac'd ſeruant diſparageth his Maſters houſe-keeping.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The curſe of God lights on them. Wee ſay if our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, corne, cattell, or graſſe, proſper not, that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched: What? a good Farme and thriue not? ſurely Gods bleſſing is not there. It is a heauy iudgement on the enemies of the Church, <hi>to be as the graſſe vpon the houſe tops, which wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth afore it grow vp, Pſal.</hi> 129.6.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Non progredi eſt regredi.</note>4 Not to goe forward, is going backward; we cannot ſtand at a ſtay, either aſcend or deſcend; coldneſſe lets in cuſtome, and cuſtome cauſeth defending of ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let ſcruteny be made in the firſt place, let vs Miniſters try your ſufficiencies; God will one day ſearch with candles. Good gold feares not the ballance nor touch-ſtone,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> but a bankrupt abides not the counting-booke. You haue heard the fitneſſe of this duty, let ſomething be ſaid as a <hi>Iacobs</hi>-ſtaffe to take the height of your graces. I purpoſe by Gods aſſiſtance, firſt to ſpread a plaiſter, then to apply it, firſt to draw, then to ſhoote. A little to diſcouer the markes of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then to lay my finger where it ſmarts. To deliuer ſomewhat as I may ſay in <hi>complexo</hi> altogether; Know this, that growing children are hungry, they eate much and often; he waxeth but ſlowly that panteth not after the word of God, the bread of life. Furthermore, note, that as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſaith;<note place="margin">Ariſt. de ortu &amp; interit. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Augmentation keepes the ſame ſpecies, when knowledge turnes into idle diſputes, and beleeuing becomes preſuming, and a tender conſcience fals to vaine ſcruples, as we ſee in our bedlam Anabaptiſts, and phantaſticall Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, whoſe doctrine is criticall, and their conuerſations hypocriticall; here is not Augmentation, but Mutation, not cheriſhing, but changing. A true grower addes daily ſome cubit to his ſtature, and in holding the truth, he beleeues the Philoſophers prouerbe, That he can neuer offend in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8843:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
exceſſe. Againe, Philoſophy ſaith,<note place="margin">Circa quali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates bonas nemo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat in exceſſis.</note> there muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n apt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in augmentation: It is vnſeemely and monſtrous in nature, for a childe to grow in armes onely, and not in the legges, or in legs and armes, but not in body; ſo to haue more knowledge, and leſſe humility, to thriue in ioy, and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-bound and hand-bound in good workes, is neither kindly nor comfortable. Wee are to put forward the ſloweſt grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace. In a word, ſome tokens that wee are of a larger ſize, are more accidentall: as, it is a thouſand to one but our ſelues or others, or both our ſelues and others, will ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aller then wee were, and our ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>pping of thoſe euil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that were before too high for vs: So alſo growers ſhall haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, the beſt ſchollers are moſt poſed the higheſt trees ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it to windes, the diuell and his agents a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ault the richeſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ties. The hotter the day the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſter the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes; the more gracious, the more oppoſed and leſſe eſteemed of the world. Good men are like a Pyramid, the nearer heauen, the leſſe in mans eye.</p>
            <p>But we may yet ſift this poynt more narrower, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtep by ſtep. Try how thou are bettered in foure things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In <hi>Mortification,</hi> doth thy bloud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e more to ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> committed? Is it thy hearts ſolace to ſee ſuperſtition, and prophanenſſe goe downe the winde? Is thy hand and heart ſet againſt them? Doſt thou more tragically butcher thine owne euill, and is now thy coruptions ſoone cruſhed if they begin to ſwell?</p>
            <p>Secondly, In <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ification,</hi> haſt thou more ſpirituall iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to heauen? Art thou earneſter in thy thoughts and ſighes. Doth loue ſtriue for the ſtrength of a Gyant? If it be thus with thee, thou art a good tree that growes downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in roote, and vpward in body and branch.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how is it with thee in holy duties? Doſt thou <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſweepe thy heart cleaner, and adorne the inward man more then thou hadſt wont before thou commeſt to Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? Art thou more ſincere, reuerent, and deuout, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming thy ſeruices <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of old? Though Sathan knocke now at thy heart, to enter in with his baſtard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, thou
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8843:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, and reſolueſt the Miniſter ſhall plow, no more on the ſands, nor ſow on the waters, but let him ſhoot and hit the white. But principally the ſtronger Chriſtian, the mightier in Prayer. Louers loue meetings, and the neerer marriage, the oftner they meete; for in this ſenſe the prouerbe is true, <hi>After building comes begging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, there is a ſenſible mending in workes, The fatter any one is in Grace, the more hee ſweates out good workes. He hath a more quicke-edg'd purpoſe to take all occaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of doing good, hee ſpreads his wings wider to helpe more people, hee dies now like a lofty Hawke at the beſt workes, hee that before was all for good to mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which are workes good in their kinde, theſe he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes more then before, but yet withall lookes higher, and labours to ſpread Gods Goſpell, and to hoyſt vp the ſayle of drooping Religion, and with his Prayers, purſe, and power doth his endeauour to beate downe Popery, and prophaneneſſe, and <hi>to be a light to them that ſit in darkeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Antipodes,</hi> oppoſite to this doctrine, are firſt, ſuch as grow not; ſecondly, or grow but in generall graces; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or ſuch as fall backe. It blots with blame, yea, bitterly bites <hi>Non profici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> Many are as ignorant, as ſinfull, as dull, as fruitleſſe, as twenty yeares agoe; they goe round as a horſe in a mill; they goe to the Church, to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to family-prayers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne vp and downe as Ants in a Mole-hill and doe nothing, and yet thinke they haue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion enough,<note place="margin">Quomodo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſi tibi iam ſufficis. Ber. de conſid. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Such are frozen on their dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs, twice dead and pluckt vp by the rootes. Nay, we haue another gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of people that enuy the growing man. If any be like <hi>Saul</hi> among the people, higher by the head and ſhoulders in matters of Religion, he is hated; as loytering ſeruants doe their fellowes that out-worke them. Dealing with his neighbours, as a Gardner with his hedge, if any part of it out-ſprout the reſt, he clips it downe. As <hi>Eſops</hi> Foxe hauing loſt his taile, would perſwade all other Foxes to cut off their tailes.<note place="margin">Act. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs that an hinderer is the child of the deuill. As for thoſe ſilly ones that are <hi>ouer-learning and neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.7.</note> but thinkes he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8843:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhould be as <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> haue a golden bridle to ſtop his poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſt to God: Theſe are as the prouerbe is;<note place="margin">Greciſemper pueri; <hi>ſaith an Egyptian,</hi> apud Plat. in Time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Alwayes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Boyes and Trewants muſt be whipt. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly obſerues in <hi>Luke</hi> 21. the danger of a ſuckling, the ioy to haue it weined, and ſo grow vp. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaith hee feaſted when <hi>Iſaac</hi> was weined,<note place="margin">In ceruitu impij ambiulant. Eraſ. coloqui de nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frag.</note> but the child that was not weined was ouerlaid by the mother. Thou art a wicked man. Circular motion is the motion of the heauens, but not the heauenlieſt motion, nor the perfecteſt. Fruitleſſe dead trees muſt be pluckt vp. God may very well giue thee vp to hardneſſe of heart, and ſay as once a Captaine did to one of his watch, finding him a ſleepe, he flew him, ſaying, <hi>Dead I found thee, and dead Ile leaue thee;</hi> for being dead ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, God may iuſtly damne thee eternally. And ſtanding ſo worſe thou mayſt be, better thou canſt not be: The lying ſtone gathers moſſe, the ſtanding poole mudde. The bird mounting vpon wing, is out of feare, but ſitting on the ground is in danger both of ſnare and Fowlet.</p>
            <p>This Atheiſt may ſtand in his owne light, and ſpurne againſt our truth with this poore obiection; That grace is a ſimple eſſence, and not naturall, and ſo not capable of growing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that a ſimple eſſence growes not in God the fountaine, or as I may ſay in the abſtract, but ſecondari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in vs it may be further reuealed, and plentifully beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. There is a ſpirituall growing, as well as a naturall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Others ſtop the mouth of Conſcience, with this, that they know more then they did, and can talke more of Religion then they had wont, and haue more dexterity in prayer, and the like. Such muſt know that there are ſome generall gifts of grace which God beſtowes on vnregenerate men as ſuch as theſe are I haue named. There is ſauing graces, as mortification, godly ſorrow, humility, and the like; if thou mendſt in theſe laſt kindes thou art happy indeede, but if thou groweſt onely in ſuch graces, as <hi>Iudas, Achit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> or ſuch hypocrites may haue, thy ſhew is more worth then thy ſubſtance: As a Cynamon tree, thy barke is more worth then thy body. Thy flouriſhing is but as a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8843:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
quagmire growne ouer with greene graſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.6.</note> Thy growing cannot laſt, but as graſſe on the houſe top, to wither before it grow vp. A tree cut vp by the rootes, may ſprout forth leaues for a while: A man after he is dead for a time his nayles and haire may grow.</p>
            <p>As for the former, they are but as a dog in a wheele; the melancholly Stoikes went beyond them: and theſe of the latter ſort; it may be euill, is at a ſtand in them, through edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or want of occaſion; as fire may want fuell; but not one ſinne yet hath his fatall blow as <hi>Goliah</hi> had, nor ſo much as a Bucke that hath his deaths wound, though he be not yet hunted downe. I ſay in all thy flouriſhing ſhewes thou deceiueſt thy brethren with ſhadowes, and thy ſelfe with ſinne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But this is not all, we haue a diſeaſe called a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, wherein men grow, I confeſſe, but worſe. Wee haue Townes,<note place="margin">Rome.</note> Cities, Kingdomes, Perſons, as the Crab-fiſh goe backeward. Shall we begin with the worſt firſt. <hi>Rome</hi> was once famous, <hi>Her faith was ſpoken of throughout the whole world,</hi> She was beautifull in her youth. Out of her loynes ſprung worthy Martyres, and reuerend Miniſters, but now ſhe is dropt into a crooked old age, a fooliſh dotage. She hath nouriſhed in her boſome a broode of miſ-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Controuerſies, and when wee haue diſcouered their yong opinions and blinde errors, like Foxes that are hard hunted, they ſeeke intricate holes, and thorny buſhes, they hide themſelues in knotty diſtinctions: So that as one ſaith, I haue ſought <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quaeſini Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam in Roma, &amp; non inueni Romam.</note> and could not finde <hi>Rome:</hi> She will haue a Monopoly of heauen, and the priſoner at the barre will be iudge of the Law. She denies children for knowing their fathers will: She wil not onely forgiue ſinnes, but maintaine ſinnes. The Stewes yeeld good tribute to the grand-mother of ſpirituall fornications.<note place="margin">Gretſer p. <hi>159.</hi> Bell de ſummo Pontif. l. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Bannes in Tho. Aquin. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> qu. <hi>12.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> Inſt. Cath. <hi>23.</hi> Ser. <hi>12.13.</hi>
               </note> Her ſubiects muſt not obey out Princes, but depoſe them, yea, in ſome caſe kill them, though the Pope grant no ſpeciall licenſe. Yea, <hi>iure &amp; merito,</hi> ſaith <hi>Simantha.</hi> May not we ſay of her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſhields, he found them of ſiluer, and left them of braſſe; ſo that now inſtead of louing her, wee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8843:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
muſt leaue her, and obey the charge giuen by the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> Chap. 50.14. <hi>Put your ſelues in aray againſt Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon round about: all yee that bend the bow ſhoot at her, ſpare no arrowes, for ſhe hath ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">England.</note> Let this be <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> diſeaſe alone. But as for the reformed Churches, let them ride on with their honour, and good proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity haue they: Farre be it from them with <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> Sunne to goe backeward. Yet if we looke into the generall decay of godlineſſe and vertue, we may with teares lament and ſay, That at the beginning men were Gyants in body, but now Gyants in ſinne.</p>
            <p>Common principles of honeſty are become vnto many,<note place="margin">Mali proficiunt boni deficiunt. Ber.</note> as the writings on a tombe ſtone, by much treading almoſt quite defaced. Wickedneſſe growes, goodneſſe decayes, by this cloude we may preſage a ſtorme.</p>
            <p>But of this famous Citie I hope better things.<note place="margin">London.</note> Your workes haue blazed all the Kingdome ouer, and diſplayed their branches into other lands, you haue clothed the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, fed the hungry, nurſed the fatherleſſe. And beſt of all which is put into the mouth of poſterity, you haue bought eye-ſalue, and haue ſent it to the blinde, and haue giuen Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to them that haue dwelt in the gloomy darkeneſſe of thicke ignorance. Oh let it not be ſaid that you retyre, or grow not on in grace and in charity as well as in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Let it not be ſaid that you feed the poore ſparingly, and plentifully feaſt the rich, who as Tennis-players, can bandy to you againe. As <hi>Rachel</hi> diſliked her owne barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo did her husband: ſo doe you your fruitleſneſſe. Principally haue a care ſo to honour God with your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as to ſend faithfull labourers into his Vineyard. I haue obſerued my ſelfe dwelling in a Countrey where Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ignorance doth lamentably flouriſh, and their neſts are for the moſt part in the Pariſh of ſome tenne pound Leuite, and wee ſhall often heare that in thoſe places, ſome one or other is drawne to the ſuperſtitious faction; and no maruell when mens mindes are as <hi>tabula nuda,</hi> fit for any impreſſion, &amp; ſo imbrace that Religion which is next to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be it what it will. Many of you may ſay with <hi>Dauid; Thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8843:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
tookeſt me from behinde the ewes;</hi> you had poore beginnings, and now God hath ſpread your tables, and fild full your cups. This life is a iourney, heauen our ayme; be a <hi>viaticum</hi> to poore Trauellers, let your purſes hire Preachers, and ſend the Goſpell where it is not, that <hi>Romes</hi> ſuperſtitions may bee baniſhed from this Land, and thereby ſinne and ſinners may be daſhed out of countenance. Truely I may ſay as the Diſciples did of the Aſſe. <hi>The Lord hath neede of him.</hi> Many good deſires are among your poore Countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but in many places for want of preaching (the fuell for that fire) all goes out:<note place="margin">Iſa. 37.3.</note> and as <hi>Hezekias</hi> ſaid, <hi>The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are come to the births, and there is no ſtrength to bring forth.</hi> Poore ſoules are ſo wounded by ſinne, that they need lie vnder the Phyſitians hand. The Prouerbe in this ſenſe is falſe.<note place="margin">Homo ſine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore eſt vt cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus ſine doctore. Aug de temp. Joſephus l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Miſere viuit qui medicè viuit;</hi> For man without a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is as a blind ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without a guide, ſaith <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> And how can men but ſleep when the candle is out? <hi>Ioſephus</hi> thought that when God ſhewed to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould goe to battell, it was thus, the Prieſt ſhould put on the Ephod, &amp; if the pretious ſtones ſhined, they need not feare their foes; but I am ſure, that if our pretious ſtones ſhine, I meane Gods Word, we neede not feare Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts kings of the earth. Well then, though it hath beene ſaid that Popery like <hi>Leah</hi> was bleare-eyed, yet fruitfull, and we faire as <hi>Rachell,</hi> but barren, Oh put you that ſong in our mouthes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.9.</note> 
               <hi>that the barren he maketh to keepe houſe to bee a ioyfull mother of children,</hi> then God ſhall haue glory, wee comfort, you profit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Magiſtrates.</note>But ſince I haue begun to ſpeake, let me ſay on. May it not be ſaid of ſome of our Magiſtrates executing of Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Quorum primus impetus plus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat quam viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſecundus minus quam fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minarum.</note> as is ſaid of the Frenchmens fight? At the firſt ſtronger then men, at the laſt weaker then women. Our Lawes the Axe-tree of our eſtate, on whoſe firmeneſſe wee mooue, vpon whoſe boſome the Church leanes, or either are as a ruſty clocke that goes not, often time for flouriſhing, not for fight. If lawes be put in execution, alas, but for a while, we may ſay as <hi>Fabias</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hannibals</hi> Armie,<note place="margin">Ad ſpecimen non ad vulnus Cic. de orat.</note> like a fire of ſtraw, makes a great blaze, but is quickely out: like the leaping of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8843:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
locuſt that flirts vp a little, and quickly downe,<note place="margin">Locuſtarum ſaltus Greg. Moral. l. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> or as the Planets in their Epicycles, ſometimes aſcending, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſcending.</p>
            <p>Let not prophanneſſe get the vpper hand, nor Popery nor carnall ſecurity, which as <hi>Prometheus</hi> his vulture eate out the heart of Religion, wee may feare, wee may ſay of them as men doe of ſnow when it melts not, that it lies for more. For Gods ſake you that are our <hi>Herculeſſes</hi> againſt theſe Gyants, bring downe her that ſits as a Queene, let not the people ſay of you, as men doe of a dead Hawke, a good one if ſhe were aliue. Let your faith out-looke your eyes, and march on valiantly.</p>
            <p>As for vs Miniſters,<note place="margin">Miniſters.</note> we ſhould be knowne as <hi>Aarons</hi> rod was, by bloſſomming and fruit, and like <hi>Nabuchadnezzars</hi> Ouen, ſeauen-times hotter then others. God would haue his meſſengers as an Emperour would haue his wife, without fault, or ſuſpicion of fault. We ſhould haue life in our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and doctrine in our life; but we haue many like a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, cryes on euery ſteeple Eaſt, Weſt, North and South, but hauing got her prey ſhe lies downe vnder a ſunny banke, and yee heare no more of her; ſo many Preachers ſpare no paines in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, till they be warme in ſome fat Parſonage, then like <hi>Demas,</hi> they embrace this preſent world: as the Eagle they flie high, and haue no eye to their neſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.5.6.</note> It is a iudgement when the tongue cleaues to the roofe of the mouth. When like the Storke, haue a ſweet voyce being yong, but a hoarſe one in old age, they either Preach not at all, or as lightning, onely flaſheth, but warmes not, and truely how can it be that the cold can warme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and he that is dead can quicken others?</p>
            <p>To end with priuate men.<note place="margin">Priuate Chriſtians.</note> How many Profeſſors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, with <hi>Lots</hi> wife haue lookt backe? let theſe know that many ſet out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that neuer ſaw the land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> ſome like <hi>Iohn</hi> march furiouſly, yet ſit downe and catch cold, and fall into a conſumption. Some now and then ſmite ſinne a little, as a mother doth a childe that ſhames her, but loue it well enough; others wound ſinne a little but will not kill it. When <hi>Eliſha</hi> bad <hi>Ioaſh</hi> take his arrowes &amp; ſmite on the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8843:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ground, and be ſmote thrice and ſtaid. <hi>The man of God was wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King 13.19.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid, thou ſhouldeſt haue ſmitten fiue or ſixe times, then hadſt thou ſmitten</hi> Syria <hi>till thou hadſt conſumed it:</hi> So if men would but giue their corruption more deadly wounds, they need not be like a Hackney, that tires in the heate of the day, or a dull Aſſes trot, that will not laſt long, or like the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> are armed, and carry bowes, yet turne backe in the day of battell; yea, deale vnfaithfully, <hi>and turne aſide like a deceitfull bow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 78.9.</note> We muſt tell to theſe ſinking-downe eſtates, that little decayes will proue great breaches; ſlidings leade to fallings; indifferency to ſenceleſneſſe.</p>
            <p>The more a man is inlightened, the worſe hee is falling backe. A candle neuer enlightened ſmels not, but being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, and blowne out, then it ſtinkes. The back-ſliders in the ſeauenth perſecution,<note place="margin">Fox Act. Mon.</note> were puniſhed with ſtrange diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and euill ſpirits. When Cranes flye backewards, it is a ſigne of a tempeſt.<note place="margin">Aelian l. <hi>3.</hi> c <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> There is nothing but ſoule weather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, for him that hath broken couenant with God. When loue tokens are ſent home, we ſay a match is broken. The Lord dwels not in that heart, that hath the goodneſſe remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of it. When we come into the Kings Pallace, and ſee all the ſumptuous Hangings taken downe; we conclude the King is remouing of his lodging. When wee haue ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred God out of our hearts, our caſe is miſerable: It is a wondrous danger of a heate to take cold. The <hi>Nouatian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, a great ſect, and many learned men were of them, held, that a reuolter could not bee receiued againe: howſoeuer I abhorre their bleare-eyed error, becauſe I here God ſay, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne O back ſliding Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 3.2.</note> yet neuertheleſſe there is ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate turnings, and Meandry windings, that few returne; none without much ſorrow and ſmart:<note place="margin">Hierome.</note> 
               <hi>Origens</hi> lamentation is wofull, and may affright a faller-backe: ſuch mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as a broken legge, wil paine in ill weather. <hi>Yet O Lord there is mercy with thee, that thou maiſt be feared.</hi> The chiefe Phyſitian of the ſoule hath ſcored vs out a way for deliuery, <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.5. firſt, <hi>Remember whence thou art fallen:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Repent, cry out againſt this ſinne, hate it, loathe it:</hi> laſtly, <hi>and doe thy firſt worke:</hi> neuer reſt till thou haſt got thy former ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8843:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>To theſe I may adde three more; firſt. Doe all this quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. A candle put out, blow the match quickly, and it may enlighten: wee are like ſluggards, the longer we lye in bed, are vnwillinger to riſe: Secondly, ill company is as ill aire, or ill dyet to a man in a conſumption, which will hinder his health, not better him: Laſtly, know God loues vs not the worſe, if we heartily mourne for our faylings, and flye to him. Chriſt calles his Spouſe, <hi>faire pleaſant, O loue for delights Cant.</hi> 7.6. although Chap. 5. ſhe had caught a fall and mar'd her face.</p>
            <p>Hauing now as a Hawke ſtrucke my talents into the face <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> of ſeuerall offenders; let me ring my ſiluer bels in the cares of a growing good man. It is pitty hee ſhould goe without his due: If it be betweene thy fleſh and ſpirit, as was betweene the houſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Now there was long warre betweene the houſe of</hi> Saul, <hi>and the houſe of</hi> Dauid, <hi>but</hi> Dauid <hi>waxed ſtronger, and the houſe of</hi> Saul <hi>waxed weaker and weaker:</hi> If thy fleſh be tamer, thy ſpirit ſtronger; ſo that thou canſt feele olde age, as well by the ſtrength of the ſoule, as the weakeneſſe of the body: Thy Conſcience, Faith, Loue, and all other graces are mightier, and as it were, vp in a ſwarme in thee: Thou art more watchfull then before: A childe, the older it growes, the leſſe it ſleepes. Thou that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore waſt afraid to follow God in the darke, but now art as a Sea-card needle, ſtandeſt in the greateſt tempeſts; we haue for thee a neaſt of young ioyes, we open a mine of gold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and tell thee thou art a true Chriſtian, croſſes cannot cruſh thee: God bindes thee vp among his iewels, and hath made more promiſes to doe thee good, then euer hee made to hold vp the pillars of the world.</p>
            <p>Some it may be accuſeth himſelfe, alas, I cannot grow,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> oh would to God I were better.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that Grace growes but ſlowly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>  and loſeth ground of time. Againe, the blade ſprings, whilſt the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman ſleepes; we may be better, and not aware of it. Alſo there are kindes of growing; trees one while ſhoote vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, another while downe. An Apple may grow one while in greatneſſe, after in goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8843:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But I am nothing like ſo forward as I was at my firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion; my prayer is weake, my hearing dull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> What are thy cloathes too little for thee? a good ſigne of growing. But a man may abate in fiue reſpects of his former forwardneſſe, and be no back-ſlider; Firſt, ſo farre as it was new to vs: the lame man, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. leapt at his firſt curing, we muſt not ſuppoſe that he did alwaies afterwards in his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, leape: The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at their deliuery out of <hi>Babylons</hi> captiuity, their mouthes were filled with laughter, and their tongues with ioy; we may not ſuppoſe that they alwaies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did nothing but laugh: The Sunne is more acceptable at the riſing, then at the ſetting. Secondly, ſo farre as was to by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends: we may heare a Preacher ſet forth the bleſſings that attend godlineſſe; as Peace, Wealth, comfort in our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the like: whereupon wee cheerefully ſet about all Gods buſineſſe; but our Lord ſeeing our vnfitneſſe to haue theſe outward bleſſings, and ſo cuts vs ſhort of them: wee may then abate of our forwardneſſe, ſo farre as theſe ends did ſpur vs on, and be no back-ſliders. Thirdly, we may ſtop ſo farre as blinde zeale puts vs forward, and bee neuer the worſe. A good man in his conuerſion, his fleſh is as the fleſh of a young childe; very tender, being but as it were, newly wounded for ſinne. A childe in grace is as one in nature, that feares bug-beares and trifles, which men doe not. Now in what he was ouer-ſcrupulous, ouer-ſtrict, too ſtraight lac't, hee may abate vpon more knowledge, and yet ſtand his ground in chriſtianity well enough. Fourthly, hee may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage of what he is at extraordinary times, in dayes of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and yet be no faller backe. Laſtly, he may be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with troubles, or vnder a temptation, or in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall deſertion; he muſt not iudge himſelfe to be, as he then feeles himſelfe to be;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for all this, it may be ſaid of thee, euen in this caſe, as <hi>Homer</hi> ſaid of <hi>Diomedes;</hi> a little man, but a great ſoldier.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> But I in truth am worſe then I were.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It may be thou ſeeſt thy ſelfe worſe, which argues a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eye-ſight, and that a greater light is in thy heart. In the morning when the roſes of the day begin to flower, all the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8843:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
foule corners of a houſe cannot be ſeene; but when the Sunne creepes towards the higheſt Zenith of heauen, euery ſmall ſpot is apparent. Or take it for granted, thou art worſe indeed, art humbled for this, doſt ſtriue againſt it mightily, as a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling man catcheth at what he can; is there an amazed kinde of ſorrow vpon thee for it? I muſt tell thee, thou maiſt be nearer deliuery now, then euer. The diuels in the Goſpell, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tortured the poſſeſſed more, then at their going out; I haue knowne it freeze the keeneſt againſt a thaw, and grow darkeſt towards breake of day.</p>
            <p>But I ſhould proue an ill Phyſition, onely to bid you grow, and not ſet in at a dead-lift. We neede helpe to this buſineſſe,<note place="margin">Helpes to grow.</note> conſidering that grace in man is like a tender out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh hearbe brought into our countries; we ſhall haue much adoe to make it proſper. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Shun</hi> ſinne, as Ignorance, Pride, Hypocriſie, ill-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, &amp;c. Euill is a ſtep-mother to good: as an Eaſterne winde nips our bloſſomes: as ſickneſſe that keepes downe a childe; ſo doth our tranſgreſſions ſtint and ſterue our graces, and make vs vncapable of being bigger.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Get</hi> a good conſcience that will caſt vp thy accounts euery night, and reade thee a curtaine lecture for thy negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thou muſt haue good ſtore of humility;<note place="margin">Diſcendendo aſcendit.</note> by deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thou ſhalt aſcend; the low vallies are euer fruitfulleſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Labour for ſpirituall wiſedome to be led by the beſt preſidents, to take thy worke out of the beſt Samplers,<note place="margin">Poſt protogenam lincam ducere.</note> to write after the beſt coppies, to draw a line after the beſt Painter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, practiſe foure duties; firſt, Meditation; ſecondly, hearing Gods word; thirdly, Prayer; fourthly, to make a good vſe of afflictions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Meditate on Gods</item>
               <item>3 The excellency of grace.
<list>
                     <item>1 Mercies.</item>
                     <item>2 His all-ſeeing eye.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 Meditate of Gods fauour to our perſons, to our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. How many dangers haue we beene lyable vnto, haue not the Buls of <hi>Baſan</hi> comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſed vs about? yet may not our Church ſing with the Church of <hi>Iſrael. Many times haue they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8843:11"/>
afflicted me from my youth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 129.2.4.</note> 
               <hi>yet they haue not preuailed againſt me; the Lord hath cut aſunder the cords of the wicked:</hi> was not King <hi>Edward</hi> our <hi>Darius</hi> to build Gods Temple? As for Queene <hi>Maries</hi> Raigne, it is true: ſucking the bloud of the Saints, yet but ſhort, and out of thoſe aſhes had we a Phaenix, the bloud of the Martyrs was the ſeed of the Church. Did not our late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of thrice bleſſed memory, account her ſelfe as a ſheepe for the ſlaughter, yet did not ſhe outliue ſixe or ſeauen Popes? As for that cruell exploit of eighty eight:<note place="margin">Pſal. 124.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>If it had not beene the Lord who was on our ſide, they had ſwallowed vs vp quicke.</hi> What Proceſſions and Maſſes, ſaid and ſung among them, hoping their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would haue giuen them the day? but our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo apparently then tooke our part; that it is reported, <hi>the great Turke</hi> ſhould ſay, in that fight God was a <hi>Lutheran.</hi> Had not the Papiſts yet a further hope, when our Queene ſhould dye; had they not <hi>Eſaus</hi> thoughts, the dayes of mourning will come ſhortly, and then, and then, we will ſlay our brethren the Proteſtants? But our Sunne did ſet, and no night followed. As for that matchleſſe plot, the Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-treaſon; before, their practiſes were fire and fagot; now, fire and powder; they would haue brought Doomes-day vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on three Kingdomes at once: Then had the ſongs of our Temples ceaſed; we might haue named our children <hi>Ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bods;</hi> yea, when our Noble Prince tooke his late long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they clapt their wings, and began to crow: but, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 124.6.</note> 
               <hi>who hath not giuen vs as a prey to their teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abortu ſolis ad Heſperium eubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.</note>If I ſhould ſtand here a whole day, I could not recount Gods goodneſſe to vs. As the Cherubins wings hung ouer the Mercy-ſeate, ſo doth Gods mercies ouer vs. Are not wee reſerued for better times then our fore-fathers were?<note place="margin">Pro mollioribus &amp; melioribus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is.</note> where hath the Goſpell ſhined more then here? hath not a pillar of fire, and a cloud guided vs aboue threeſcore yeares? As a man that at the beginning of a cleare night counts the ſtars, but after a while, they appeare ſo faſt, that he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. Our ſtars, our Preachers, in the beginning of our late Queenes Raigne might eaſily haue beene numbred; but who can reckon vp our ſhining lampes now? So that wee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8843:11"/>
may ſay of our Land, as <hi>Siluius</hi> ſaid of <hi>Rhodes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Semper in ſole ſita eſt.</note> 
               <hi>It is alwaies in the Sunne;</hi> our Muſtard-ſeede is a ſpreading tree, and birds build in it.</p>
            <p>What muſt we ſay to all this? Heare the Apoſtles aduice, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Hauing therefore theſe promiſes, let vs perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> what are oure, <hi>promiſes?</hi> nay, hauing theſe performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let vs perfect holineſſe, and increaſe in godlineſſe. The beſt hearbs grow in the ſun-ſhine: our Summer flowers are the beſt flowers: we muſt hatch and ripen too vnder Gods wing of mercy, or we ſhall neuer be ought.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Conſider well of Gods all-ſeeing eye, and thou canſt not but mend. The maſters eye makes the horſe fat,<note place="margin">Fertillinus in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro oculus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni eſt, Plin l. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and the field fruitfull.</p>
            <p>If a Magiſtrate would but well weigh, though he be a God of men, yet he is a man of God; <hi>Ye are Gods;</hi> alas, but metaphoricall Gods, a Dietie of ſome threeſcore and tenne yeares; and then he that whileome was a Iudge,<note place="margin">Nuper Iudex eram iam Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ante tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> muſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be iudged; it would make him not winke in one cauſe, and haue <hi>Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceus</hi> eyes in another. If our great men would but dwell on theſe thoughts, they would with flaming cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſpeake for God on the Bench, and in the Parliament-houſe too.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Ponder well the excellency of Grace, and it will cauſe thee to ſtirre <hi>vp the gift of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. It eſtabliſheth the heart, and like an <hi>Atlas</hi> vnderprops vs in dangers, it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the minde, ſo that we ſhall turne no more to our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer courſe of ſinning; whereas, good nature, education, wiſedome, cannot alter one quality, but ſo as a Wolfe in Sheepe skins, will turne to his olde by as againe: The guilt of any thing will weare off: <hi>Riches will take her to her wings as an Eagle,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> on which if thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy heart, thou hangſt thy iewell at an Eagles legge that will flye away with it. All earthly things in time of miſery, is as a heape of ſnow, which melts away in a hot day, and makes the wayes miery: But grace is a cordiall in euery ſickneſſe, a houſe in euery ſtorme: In all troubles it makes the Church our Chayre, our Faith our Feaſt, and Heauen our home. Who will not worke hard for this wages, and ſow much, to reape much of this graine?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8843:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>The ſecond dutie, as a pully to ſet thy clocke on going, is a diligent hearing of Gods word, that is our foode, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. <hi>As new borne babes, deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that ye may grow thereby.</hi> There muſt be nutriment to augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; manuring makes Plants flouriſh; feeding makes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and cattell grow. Gods word is our <hi>paſci</hi> and <hi>naſci,</hi> birth and breeding: and yet alas how few reſpect it, and amongſt thoſe that are ſwift to heare, how many haue we, that are like men ſicke of an Atrophy, eate much, but thriue not? We heare much, but practiſe not; like a bul-ruſh, drie, though in a wet place.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, prayer is a ſupporting ſtone in this Building, and a good ſtake in this hedge;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.2. &amp; 2. ep. 12.</note> This the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed for our inſtruction, and the reſt of the Apoſtles toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Bona mea dona tua. Aug. vel ipſe velabipſo Aug. de doctr. Chriſt. c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5. <hi>Encreaſe our faith,</hi> for all comes from God that's good; <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollo water, but God giues the increaſe.</hi> Either it is himſelfe, or from himſelfe. Now prayer ſets God on worke, and God ſets Heauen and earth on worke. He hath pawn'd his word to heare vs. His Name is a heare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of prayers.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, make a good vſe of croſſes and troubles; let them doe the worke they are ſent for, plucke thy heart from the world, exerciſe thy faith and patience, let them driue thee to God, rowze vp thy prayer, and chaine thine eare to his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly-voyce.</p>
            <p>Grace is like ſome kinde of Fowles, the fatteſt in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt weather, as a ſea-bird that build <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neſt in a ſtorme, as a palme tree that is taller for preſſing.</p>
            <p>I haue now ſaid what I can in this point, Let vs heare the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeake,<note place="margin">Vireſcit vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Quid. Eleg.</note> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Brethren, wee exhort you by the Lord Ieſus, that yee would abound more and more;</hi> You looke how your children grow, and will now and then caſt vp your bookes to ſee how your eſtates thriue, you will walke into your Gardens and to your Countrey houſes, to view the comming forward of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and corne; for Gods ſake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſoule in the boſome, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelues good, and crowne you for doing yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8843:12"/>
into whoſe hands I commit you, the Lord of heauen make you know the things that belong to your peace, &amp; not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the day of your viſitation. Now is our Spring-time. When one is dead, his dayes of thriuing are gone.<note place="margin">Iob 14.7.10</note> 
               <hi>There is hope of a tree,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, that it may ſprought, though it be cut vp, yet by the ſent of water it will bud; but man is ſicke and dyeth, and periſheth.</hi> Whileſt we haue time let vs doe good, let our eyes be in our heads; The Lord God make vs wiſe vnto Saluation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
